# Kristopher J. Overholt

Sales and Solutions Engineer https://www.koverholt.com

Algorithmia https://www.linkedin.com/in/koverholt/

Austin, TX (Remote) https://github.com/koverholt

## **Summary of Qualifications**

10+ years of experience working with data science and data analysis with Python and R.

9+ years of working with DevOps tooling, automation, testing, and deployments.

7+ years of academic and industry teaching experience with data science and engineering coursework.

Applying Python and R to engineering problems, data analysis, and computational models.

Administration of on-premises and cloud-based Linux systems with Docker, Kubernetes, and Hadoop.

### **Education**

Ph.D. in Civil Engineering, The University of Texas at Austin, 2013

M.S. in Fire Protection Engineering, Worcester Polytechnic Institute, 2010

B.S. in Fire Protection Engineering Technology, University of Houston-Downtown, 2008

## **Certifications**

Pragmatic Marketing Certified - Level III (PMC-III) - November 2017

Texas Board of Professional Engineers Certified EIT #40629 - September 2008

## **Employment and Research Experience**

Sales and Solutions Engineer

August 2020–Present

#### Algorithmia

Austin, TX (Remote)

Helping customers benefit from our machine learning operations (MLOps) platform that manages all stages of the ML lifecycle. Working closely with sales prospects to execute on customer opportunities. Creating tailored demos that showcase the breadth and depth of our enterprise product. Creating and nurturing strong customer relationships.

Solutions Engineer

November 2018-July 2020

#### **RStudio**

Austin, TX (Remote)

Worked with customers in pre-sales and post-sales activities to integrate enterprise data science products in production environments with Python and R. Developed technical assets and documentation related to enterprise data science products. Worked closely with customer success, support, and product engineering teams. Specialized in enterprise IT infrastructure and DevOps as well as product integrations with Python, Kubernetes, Slurm, and Spark.

Senior Product Manager / Software Engineer

February 2015–October 2018

Anaconda Austin, TX

Worked with customers and users to understand market problems, then formulate and prioritize repeatable solutions in an enterprise data science platform with Python and R. Performed DevOps, automation, and QA testing for data science platform built on Docker and Kubernetes. Developed tools/products to manage Python packages across bare-metal and cloud-based clusters. Managed cluster computing products that integrate Python with Hadoop and Spark. Coordinated with product marketing team to create webinars, demonstrations, and sales collateral. Worked with customers as a solution architect for cluster computing and data analysis/engineering/model workflows.

Fire Protection Engineer / Software Engineer

May 2012–January 2015

#### National Institute of Standards and Technology

Gaithersburg, MD

Performed fire model verification and validation work for the US Nuclear Regulatory Commission (NRC) related to empirical correlations and Fire Dynamics Simulator (FDS). Worked with the FDS development team on verification and validation, continuous integration testing, and quality metrics. Conducted fire modeling studies to provide insight on the fire development and thermal conditions during firefighter fatality and injury incidents. Conducted full-scale experimental work related to improving firefighter tactics and safety. Developed sensor-based smart firefighting technology.

Graduate Research Assistant / Software Engineer

January 2010-May 2013

### The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX

Research assistant on issues related to fire modeling, inverse fire modeling problems, fire suppression systems in nuclear gloveboxes, firefighter line of duty injuries/deaths, wildland fire experiments and modeling, and positive pressure ventilation experiments and simulations.

Graduate Researcher / Software Engineer

May 2011-August 2011

## Southwest Research Institute

San Antonio, TX

Performed data analysis on the project: Reducing Uncertainty of Quantifying the Burning Rate of Upholstered Furniture. Fire modeling and data analysis work for full-scale upholstered furniture fire experiments sponsored by the National Institute of Justice (NIJ). Developed fire model simulations and guidance for the forensic investigation of fire incidents involving upholstered furniture.

Adjunct Faculty

August 2010–May 2011

#### University of Houston-Downtown

Houston, TX

Instructor for fire protection engineering courses including Fire Dynamics, Fire Modeling, Structural Fire Safety, and Advanced Problems in Fire and Safety in the Fire Protection Engineering Technology program.

Research Assistant and Teaching Assistant

August 2008–December 2009

#### Worcester Polytechnic Institute

Worcester, MA

Teaching assistant to graduate level courses in the Department of Fire Protection Engineering. Research assistant in the fire science laboratory for small-scale commodity tests, including the cone calorimeter. The goal was to better classify and protect commodity storage in warehouse facilities and predict upward flame spread rates in warehouse fires.

### **Skills and Coursework**

Python / NumPy / SciPy / pandas

Data Science Workflows

DevOps, CI/CD, and Automation

Terraform, Salt, Ansible scikit-learn / Tensorflow

 ${\bf Docker}\ /\ {\bf Container\text{-}Based\ Workflows}$ 

Hadoop Configuration and Administration

Mac OS X / Linux / Windows Django / Flask / WordPress

Matlab / LabVIEW

Small-Scale and Large-Scale Experiments

Scientific / Technical Copy Editing

Scientific / High-Performance Computing

Scientific Visualization & Data Analysis

Instrumentation and Data Collection

IATEX

Computational Fluid Dynamics

Engineering Mechanics

Heat Transfer

Combustion

Thermodynamics
Differential Equations

Incompressible Flow

Fluid Mechanics

Numerical Methods

R / Shiny / RStudio

Predictive Model Development and Deployment

Slurm and HPC Clustering Technologies

Cloud Infrastructure / AWS / GCP / Azure

Visualization: matplotlib / seaborn / ggplot Kubernetes Configuration and Administration

Hadoop / Spark / PySpark Data Analysis

Fortran / C++

Solution Architecting / Requirements Gathering

Data Analytics Platforms

NIST Fire Dynamics Simulator

CFAST / BRANZFIRE Zone Models

Performance-Based Design

Fire Dynamics

Fire Alarm Signaling Systems
Structural Design for Fire Safety

Fire Safety and Hazard Recognition

Building Fire Safety

Automatic Fire Suppression

Industrial Safety
Fire Modeling
HVAC Design

Indoor Air Quality: Transport and Control

Human Factors in Fire Safety

Human Exposure to Indoor Air Pollution

## **Teaching and Tutor Experience**

Adjunct Faculty August 2010–May 2011

Department of Engineering Technology, University of Houston–Downtown

Courses: Fire Dynamics, Fire Modeling, Structural Fire Safety

Teaching Assistant January 2010–May 2010

Department of Mechanical Engineering, The University of Texas at Austin

Courses: Heat Transfer Lab

Teaching Assistant August 2008–December 2009

Department of Fire Protection Engineering, Worcester Polytechnic Institute

Courses: Fire Dynamics, Fire Protection Systems, Building Fire Safety

Tutor and Lab Assistant August 2007–May 2008

Department of Engineering Technology, University of Houston–Downtown

## **Memberships**

Member, Society of Fire Protection Engineers, 2004–2015

Member, National Fire Protection Association, 2014–2015

Member, International Association for Fire Safety Science, 2011–2015

President, SFPE UT Student Chapter, 2010–2012

President, SFPE WPI Student Chapter, 2009

Founding President, SFPE UHD Student Chapter, 2007

### **Honors and Awards**

Jack Bono Award for Engineering Communications, Society of Fire Protection Engineers, 2017

Best Thesis Award "Excellence in Research", International Association for Fire Safety Science, 2014

Harry C. Bigglestone Award for Excellence in Communication of Fire Protection Concepts,

Fire Technology, National Fire Protection Association, 2013

Honorable Mention, NSF Graduate Research Fellowship, 2009 & 2010

2nd place, Combustion Art Competition, 6th U.S. National Combustion Meeting, 2009

Gerald M. Maatman Fellowship, Kemper Foundation; Fire Science Laboratory, WPI, 2009

Outstanding Graduate - Safety and Fire Engineering Technology, UHD, 2008

LS-AMP Outstanding Scholar Award - Highest GPA in Engineering Technology Dept., UHD, 2008

Brown Foundation Leadership Award – Scholars Academy, UHD, 2007 & 2008

Hat's Off Award, Society of Fire Protection Engineers Annual Conference, 2007

Outstanding Student – Safety and Fire Engineering Technology, UHD, 2006 & 2007

Louis Stokes Alliance Minority Participation Scholarship, National Science Foundation, 2006

Red Rose Scholarship, UHD, 2006

Rookie of the Year, Klein Fire Department, 2002

### Volunteerism

Webmaster Chair, Texas Exes Highland Lakes Chapter; Marble Falls, TX, 2019-Present

Technology Support Team, St. Peter's Lutheran Church; Marble Falls, TX, 2019–Present

President, Overholser Family Association; Lancaster County, PA, 2017–2019

Webmaster, North Austin Civic Association; Austin, TX, 2010–2013

Orphanage work, Casa Hogar Douglas; Monterrey, Mexico, January 2007

Community Involvement Day; UHD, September 2006

Ed's Bayou Cleanup; UHD, Spring 2006

Emergency Disaster Preplanning; Loving and Caring Arms Adult Care Facility, March 2006

Tactical Suppression Firefighter, Klein Fire Dept. Station 32; Houston, TX, 2002–2005

Fire alarm system upgrades, Sweetwater Christian School; Houston, TX, 2005